<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1889 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1889.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3489 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3489.xml">


<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-behave-turn SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-behave-turn">
]>
<!-- $Id -->
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<!--<?rfc strict="yes" ?>-->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-rescorla-mmusic-ice-passive-00.txt" ipr="full3978">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Passive ICE">Implementing Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE) in Passive-Only Mode</title>

    <author fullname="Eric Rescorla" initials="E." surname="Rescorla">
      <organization>Network Resonance</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2483 E. Bayshore #212</street>

          <city>Palo Alto</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94303</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ekr@networkresonance.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="06" month="November" year="2006" />

    <abstract>
      <t>Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE) is a technique
      for discovering a set of addresses which two peers can use to
      communicate, even in the face of topological obstacles such as
      NATs. Because the topologies in which ICE may be used are 
      complex, a full ICE implementation is also fairly complex.
      Implementation which will only be deployed in settings
      where they have public addresses (e.g., SIP-PSTN
      gateways) can, however, be 
      substantially simpler. This document describes a subset of
      ICE suitable for such implementations.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
    <t>Network Address Translation (NAT) devices are a major obstacle
    to protocols in which a pair of network elements need to form
    a direct connection. In many cases, such elements are able to 
    talk to each other directly using a signalling protocol such
    as SIP <xref target="RFC3261"/> but for efficiency reasons want
    to send data (e.g., media over RTP <xref target="RFC1889"/>)
    directly.
    </t>
    <t>A number of techniques are available for traversing NATs,
    but entities need a mechanism for discovering which technique 
    will work in its specific environment (and its peer's environment).
    Internet Connectivity Establishment (ICE) <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice"/> is such a technique.
    </t>
    <t>
    The basic principle behind ICE is that each entity collects all 
    the addresses on which it might potentially be able to send and
    receive data. These may include its local address, addresses
    discovered via STUN <xref target="RFC3489"/> or addresses provided
    by media relays <xref target="I-D.ietf-behave-turn"/>. The
    peers then exchange these candidate addresses and try each 
    potential pairing in priority order
    until they find one that is satisfactory.
    </t>
    <t>
    During the design of ICE, many implementors expressed concern
    about the complexity of the protocol and the difficulty of
    implementing it. This draft specifies a compatible
    simplified subset
    of ICE called "Passive ICE" which is suitable for implementations
    which will always be operated with public IP addresses. 
    One particular environment where Passive ICE is intended
    to be useful is in SIP-PSTN gateways which are generally
    directly connected to the Internet.
    </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Conventions Used In This Document">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="section.sec" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
    Security considerations go here
    </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgments">
    <t>
    Some people probably helped me.
    </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <section title="How to Read This Document">
  <t>
  This document is intended to mostly relieve the implementor of a passive-only
  ICE implementation from the burden of having to read and understand all of
  RFC XXXX [[Insert ICE RFC # here]
  <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice"/>. However, it is not intended to be a
  standalone document. Rather it is intended to be read in conjunction
  with RFC XXXX. We assume that the reader is roughly
  familiar with how ICE works and has read at least Sections 1-3 of 
  RFC XXXX.
  </t>
  <t>
  Section <xref target="main.body"/>, contains a description of the
  responsibilities of a POII (POII). Each section
  follows the same pattern: expository text followed by a pointer
  to the relevant section of RFC XXXX. 
  </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Overview of Operation">
  <t>
  A POII behaves much like a normal ICE
  implementation, with three major differences:
  </t>
  <list style="symbols">
  <t>It only gathers candidate addresses from its own interfaces.</t>
  <t>It cannot be a controlling endpoint.</t>
  <t>It does not generate periodic checks but only responds to periodic
checks from other endpoints.</t>
  </list>
  <t>
  A POII can interoperate with a normal ICE
  implementation. Two POIIs will 
  interoperate but will not do ICE.
  </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Passive-Only ICE Specification" anchor="main.body">
  <section title="Gathering Candidates">
  <t>
  Like any ICE implementation, a POII gathers candidates. However,
  unlike full ICE implementations, a POII gathers them only from
  its locally attached interfaces (host candidates). Other kinds
  of candidates are not necessary because a POII by definition
  has a public IP address.
  </t>
  <t>
  See: Sections 2.1 (paragraphs 1,2), 5.1 (paragraphs 1, 2, 3)
  </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Setting Priorities">
  <t>
  As with full-mode ICE, the candidates must be prioritized. 
  However, a POII will only have one candidate type: host.
  The type preference SHOULD be set to 126.
  </t>
  <t>The endpoint SHOULD set the local preferences counting down from
  65535.  Thus, a dual-homed endpoint SHOULD use the values
  65535 and 65534.
  </t>
  <t>
  The component IDs are set as in RFC XXXX.
  </t>
  <t>
  Using these settings, a singly-homed endpoint which wished to do
  RTP only would have a single candidate with priority 2130706431 
  (0x7effffff)
  A dual-homed endpoint which preferred interface A to interface
  B and wanted to do both RTP and RTCP would have:
  </t>
  <texttable>
  <ttcol>Interface</ttcol><ttcol>Protocol</ttcol><ttcol>Priority</ttcol>
  <c>A</c><c>RTP</c><c>2130706431 (0x7effffff)</c>
  <c>A</c><c>RTCP</c><c>2130706430 (0x7efffffe)</c>
  <c>B</c><c>RTP</c><c>2130706175 (0x7efffefe)</c>
  <c>B</c><c>RTCP</c><c>2130706174 (0x7efffefe)</c>
  </texttable>
  <t>
  See: Section 5.2.
  </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Encoding Candidates in SDP">
  <t>
  Once the candidates are gathered, a POII must encode them in an SDP
  offer or answer. All candidates MUST be marked as host candidates.
  </t>
  <t>
  In addition, a POII must set the "a=ice-passive" session-level
  attribute in order to indicate that it is not a full ICE implementation.
  </t>
  <t>
  See: Sections 5.4, 6.7
  </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Receiving SDP Offers/Answers">
  <t>
  [TODO]
  </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Performing Checks">
  <t>
  A POII does not perform periodic checks, but it MUST respond to 
  periodic checks and perform triggered checks. In order to do so,
  it MUST maintain a primitive check list. However, unlike a full
  implementation, this list is initially empty and is populated
  only by the receipt of periodic checks from the peer endpoint.
  </t>
  <t>
  <section title="Processing Periodic Checks">
  <t>
  During ICE discovery, a POII will Binding Requests on the bases
  of some or all of the candidates it included in its most
  recent offer or answer. When such a Binding Request is 
  received, the POII MUST:
  </t>
  <list style="symbols">
  <t>Generate a STUN binding response.</t>
  <t>If the candidate pair is not currently on the check list
     add it to the check list and start a triggered check for this
     candidate pair.</t>
  </list>
  <t>
  See: Sections 8.2 (paragraphs 1-6).
  </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Performing Triggered Checks">
  <t>
  Triggered checks are performed exactly as described in RFC XXX.
  </t>
  <t>
  See: Section 8.1.
  </t>
  <section title="Concluding ICE">
  <t>
  A POII may not be a controlling ICE endpoint. Therefore, from
  its perspective ICE terminates when each component has at least
  one Valid candidate pair marked selected (i.e., a check on
  that candidate pair has been received with the USE-CANDIDATE
  attribute set). 
  </t>
  <t>
  See: Section 9.
  </t>
  </section>
  </section>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC1889;
      &RFC2119;
      &I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice;
    </references>
    <references title="Informational References">

      &RFC3261;
      &RFC3489;
      &I-D.ietf-behave-turn;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:2
sgml-indent-data:nil
sgml-parent-document:nil
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
End:
-->

